Register of the Nicolae Titulescu Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Nicolae Titulescu papers,
1923-1938
74098
Titulescu, Nicolae, 1882-1941
17 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope, 4 microfilm reels (7.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Diaries, correspondence, memoranda, reports, writings, clippings, and printed matter, relating to Romanian politics and diplomacy, and to Romanian-Soviet negotiations, 1931-1932. Also available on microfilm (24 reels).
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Access
May be used only if name of user and copy of any publication based on the collection are made available to Mme M. Y. Antoniade.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1974.
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Alternative Forms of Material Available
Also available on microfilm (24 reels).
Biographical Note
1882 March 4 Born, Craiova, Romania
1904 Obtained juris doctorate from the University of Paris
1905 Appointed law professor, University of Iasi, Romania
1909 Appointed law professor, University of Bucarest, Romania
1912 Elected to the Romanian Parliament
1917 Minister of Finance
1918 Forced to leave Romania for exile in Paris
1918-1919 Member, Romanian National Committee in Paris
1920 June 4 Appointed delegate to the Paris Peace Conference. Participated in the negotiations and signed the Treaty of Trianon for Romania
1920-1922 Minister of Finance
1920-1932 Permanent Delegate to the League of Nations
1922-1927, 1928-1932 Ambassador to Great Britain
1926-1929 Romanian representative in the Council of the League of Nations
1927 July - 1928 July Minister of Foreign Affairs
1930 March Romanian delegate to the Conference on Reparations in the Hague
1930 and 1931 President of the 11th and 12th sessions of the Assembly of the League of Nations
1932 October - 1933 January Minister of Foreign Affairs in Juliu Maniu Cabinet
1933 January-November Minister of Foreign Affairs in Vaida-Voevod Cabinet
1933 June Chief of the Romanian Delegation to the Monetary and Economic Conference in London
1933 November - 1934 January Minister of Foreign Affairs in Ion G. Duca Cabinet
1934 January Minister of Foreign Affairs in Gheorghe Tatarescu Cabinet
1934 January - 1936 August Minister of Foreign Affairs in reconstructed Cabinet
1936 August Dismissed from the government Appointed Senator for Life
1941 March 17 Died, Cannes, France
Scope and Content Note
Diaries, correspondence, memoranda, reports, writings, clippings, and printed matter, relating to Romanian politics and diplomacy, and to Romanian-Soviet negotiations, 1931-1932. Also available on microfilm (24 reels).
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
League of Nations.; Balkan entente, 1934-1941.; Little entente, 1920-1939.; Great Britain.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--Romania.; Romania.; Romania--Foreign relations--Great Britain.; Romania--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; Romania--Politics and government.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--Foreign relations--Romania.
Occupations
Diplomats--Romania.; Statesmen--Romania.
Series Description
- Biographical File, 1913-1972. (Box 1)
  Biographical material, certificates, clippings, commendations, congratulatory letter, curricula vitae, invitation, lists, official government documents, and tributes, relating to Nicolae Titulescu's life and career as diplomat and statesman, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Notebooks, 1923-1931. (Box 2-13)
  Carbon copies of handwritten personal notes, correspondence, memoranda, telegrams, etc., arranged chronologically into 187 notebooks
- Correspondence, 1921-1939. (Box 13-14)
  Correspondence, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Speeches and Writings, 1925-1937. (Box 14-16)
  Interview, memoirs, tributes, speeches, and writings, arranged chronologically by title
- Subject File, 1919-1947. (Box 16-17)
  Charts, correspondence, memoranda, articles, reports, telegrams, minutes of meetings, lists, notes, official government documents, clippings and other printed matter, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Photographs, n.d. (Box 17 and photo file)
  One print of a painting by Brenner depicting the inn in Talloires, France, where Nicolae Titulescu met secretly with Maksim Litvinov on May 28, 1937; and one print of a portrait depicting Nicolae Titulescu, n.d.
- Microfilm, n.d. (Microfilm-cabinet Microfilm cabinet)
  Four microfilm reels of Nicolae Titulescu's notebooks
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1913-1972., See also SUBJECT FILE/Trials (Box 1)
  - Certificates, commendations, congratulatory letter (Folder 1: 1)
  - Clippings on Nicolae Titulescu and Romanian politics
    - Foreign press
      - Undated (Folder 1: 2)
      - 1913-1929 (Folder 1: 3)
      - 1931-1938 (Folder 1: 4)
    - Romanian press
      - Undated (Folder 1: 5)
      - 1924-1934 (Folder 1: 6)
      - 1936 August-October (after the dismissal of Nicolae Titulescu from the government) (Folder 1: 7)
  - Curricula vitae (Folder 1: 8)
  - Invitation from Gustav Stresemann to Nicolae Titulescu to come to Berlin, 1928 January (Folder 1: 9)
  - Subject file
    - Biography. (Folder 1: 10)
      Various documents used by Jacques de Launay for his editing of Titulescu et l'Europe
    - City of "Slatina" renamed "Titulescu," 1920 (Folder 1: 11)
    - Government service., See also Clippings
      - Document signed by President of the Council, Gheorghe Tatarescu, and two other members, in the name of the government, supporting the policy of Nicolae Titulescu, 1936 July 14 (in French) (Folder 1: 12)
      - Letter from the Regency Council asking Nicolae Titulescu to Bucarest for consultation, 1928 (Folder 1: 13)
      - Lists of foreign representatives in London, 1925 April (Folder 1: 14)
      - Official communiqué in the hand of Gheorghe Tatarescu expressing to Nicolae Titulescu, in the name of the government, "his regards and confidence," n.d. (in French) (Folder 1: 15)
      - Telegram from Gheorghe Tatarescu to Nicolae Titulescu, announcing to the latter that he is no longer part of the government, 1936 August 29 (in French) (Folder 1: 16)
    - Nomination of Nicolae Titulescu as Romanian delegate to the Conference on the codification of international law in The Hague, 1930 March (Folder 1: 17)
    - Travel - United States, 1924 December - 1925 January. (Folder 1: 18)
      Clippings
  - Tributes (in Romanian and French)
    - Undated (Folder 1: 19)
    - 1951-1964 (Folder 1: 20)
    - 1966 (Folder 1: 21)
    - 1967-1972 (Folder 1: 22)
- NOTEBOOKS, 1923-1931 (187 notebooks)., Please consult the Archives staff for an additional list of the most important items in this series (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - 1923
    - April-June (#1-3)
    - June-September (#4-6) (Folder 2: 2)
    - October-November (#7-9) (Folder 2: 3)
  - 1923 November - 1924 February (#10-12) (Folder 2: 4)
  - 1924
    - February-April (#13-15) (Folder 2: 5)
    - April-May (#16-18) (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - May-June (#19-20) (Folder 3: 2)
    - June-July (#21-23) (Folder 3: 3)
    - August-September (#24-26) (Folder 3: 4)
    - September-October (#27-29) (Folder 3: 5)
    - October-November (#30-32) (Folder 3: 6)
    - November-December (#33-35) (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - December (#36) (Folder 4: 2)
  - 1925
    - February-March (#37-39) (Folder 4: 3)
    - March-April (#40-42) (Folder 4: 4)
    - May-June (#43-45) (Folder 4: 5)
    - June (#46) (Folder 4: 6)
    - June-July (#47-49) (Folder 4: 7)
    - July-September (#50-52) (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - September-October (#53-55) (Folder 5: 2)
    - October (#56-58) (Folder 5: 3)
    - November-December (#59) (Folder 5: 4)
  - 1925 December - 1926 January (#60-62) (Folder 5: 5)
  - 1926
    - January-February (#63-65) (Folder 5: 6)
    - February-March (#66-68) (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - March-May (#69-71) (Folder 6: 2)
    - May-June (#72-74) (Folder 6: 3)
    - June-September (#75-77) (Folder 6: 4)
    - September-October (#78-80) (Folder 6: 5)
    - November (#81-83) (Folder 6: 6)
    - December (#84-86) (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - 1927
    - January (#87-89) (Folder 7: 2)
    - February (#90-92) (Folder 7: 3)
    - March-May (#93-95) (Folder 7: 4)
    - May-July (#96-98) (Folder 7: 5)
    - July-October (#99-101) (Folder 7: 6)
    - October-December (#102-104) (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - 1927 December - 1928 January (#105-107) (Folder 8: 2)
  - 1928
    - January-March (#108-110) (Folder 8: 3)
    - March
      - (#111-113) (Folder 8: 4)
      - (#114-116) (Folder 8: 5)
      - (#117-119) (Folder 8: 6)
      - (#120-122) (Box-folder 9: 1)
    - March-April (#123-125) (Folder 9: 2)
    - April (#126-128) (Folder 9: 3)
    - April-May (#129-131) (Folder 9: 4)
    - May (#132-134) (Folder 9: 5)
    - May-August (#136-138) (Folder 9: 6)
    - August (#138-139) (Box-folder 10: 1)
    - August-October (#140-142) (Folder 10: 2)
    - October-November (#143) (Folder 10: 3)
  - 1928 December - 1929 January (#144-146) (Folder 10: 4)
  - 1929
    - January (#147) (Folder 10: 5)
    - January-March (#148-150) (Folder 10: 6)
    - March-May (#151-153) (Folder 10: 7)
    - May-August (#154-156) (Box-folder 11: 1)
    - July-September (#157-159) (Folder 11: 2)
    - September-October (#160-162) (Folder 11: 3)
    - October-December (#163-165) (Folder 11: 4)
  - 1929 December - 1930 January (#166-169) (Folder 11: 5)
  - 1930 (Box-folder 12: 1)
    - February-May (#169-171)
    - May-October (#172-174) (Folder 12: 2)
    - October-December (#175-177) (Folder 12: 3)
  - 1930 December - 1931 January (#178-180) (Folder 12: 4)
  - 1931
    - January-March (#181-183) (Folder 12: 5)
    - May-September (#185-187) (Box-folder 13: 1)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1921-1939
  - Alexandra, Mother (Folder 13: 2)
  - Antonescu, Ion, Colonel, 1924-1928 (Folder 13: 3)
  - Apponyi, n.d. (Folder 13: 4)
  - Argesenau, G., Colonel, 1921-1928 (Folder 13: 5)
  - Argetoianu, Constantin, 1923-1928 (Folder 13: 6)
  - Asquith, Herbert Henry, 1924-1925 (Folder 13: 7)
  - Averescu, Alexandru, General, 1925-1931 (Folder 13: 8)
  - Balbo, Italo, 1931 (Folder 13: 9)
  - Benes, Edvard, 1925-1930 (Folder 13: 10)
  - Blum, Léon, n.d. (Folder 13: 11)
  - Bourne, Cardinal, 1924 (Folder 13: 12)
  - Branting, H. J., 1924 (Folder 13: 13)
  - Bratianu, Jean, 1924 (Folder 13: 14)
  - Bratianu, Vintila, 1922-1929 (Folder 13: 15)
  - Briand, Aristide, 1928-1929 (Folder 13: 16)
  - Buzdugan, George, 1928-1930 (Folder 13: 17)
  - Cantacuzino, Alexandru, n.d. (Folder 13: 18)
  - Carol II, King of Romania, 1921-1931 (Folder 13: 19)
  - Cecil, Robert, 1923-1931 (Folder 13: 20)
  - Chamberlain, Austen, 1925-1928 (Folder 13: 21)
  - Churchill, Winston, 1929 (Folder 13: 22)
  - Ciotosi, Y. N., 1929 (Folder 13: 23)
  - Connaught, Arthur, Duke of, 1925-1926 (Folder 13: 24)
  - Curtius, Julius, 1929 (Folder 13: 25)
  - Curzon, George Nathaniel, 1922 - Includes condolence letter to Mrs. Curzon, 1925 (Folder 13: 26)
  - Disarmament Committee of the Women's International Organizations (Geneva), n.d. (Folder 13: 27)
  - Dolni, Angelo M., 1928-1930 (Folder 13: 28)
  - Doumer, Paul, 1921 (Folder 13: 29)
  - Drummond, Eric, 1926-1930 (Folder 13: 30)
  - Duca, Ion G., 1923-1931 (Folder 13: 31)
  - L'Écho de Paris, 1924 (Folder 13: 32)
  - Gafencu, Grigore, 1929-1930 (Folder 13: 33)
  - Ghika, Dimitrie, 1928-1931 (Folder 13: 34)
  - Gnani, M., 1923-1926 (Folder 13: 35)
  - Grandi, Dino, 1928 (Folder 13: 36)
  - Great Britain. Embassy (France), 1928 (Folder 13: 37)
  - Helene, Princess of Romania, 1925-1927 (Folder 13: 38)
  - Henderson, n.d. (Folder 13: 39)
  - Herriot, Édouard, 1924-1930 (Folder 13: 40)
  - Ileana, Princess of Romania, 1928-1931., See Alexandra, Mother
  - Institut Français de Hautes Études en Roumanie, 1930 (Folder 13: 41)
  - International League Against Racism (Paris), 1938 (Folder 13: 42)
  - Ionesco, Take, 1920-1921 (Folder 13: 43)
  - Iorga, Nicolae, 1924-1931 (Folder 13: 44)
  - Jouvenel, Henry de, 1924-1930 (Folder 13: 45)
  - Kellogg, Frank B., 1927 (Folder 13: 46)
  - League of Nations. Délégation syro-palestinienne (Geneva), 1929 (Folder 13: 47)
  - League of Nations. President, 1930 (Folder 13: 48)
  - Lloyd George, David, 1922 (Folder 13: 49)
  - Lloyd George, Margaret, 1931 (Folder 13: 50)
  - Loucheur, Louis, 1930 (Folder 13: 51)
  - McDonald, Ramsay, 1925 (Box-folder 14: 1)
  - Maniu, Juliu, 1928-1939 (Folder 14: 2)
  - Manoilescu, M., 1925-1926 (Folder 14: 3)
  - Marie, Queen of Romania, 1924-1931 (Folder 14: 4)
  - Masaryk, Jan, 1926-1930 (Folder 14: 5)
  - Mironescu, G. G., 1929-1931 (Folder 14: 6)
  - Mironescu, M., 1930 (Folder 14: 7)
  - Mitilineu, J., 1927-1930 (Folder 14: 8)
  - Monnet, Jean, n.d. (Folder 14: 9)
  - Murray, Gilbert, 1931 (Folder 14: 10)
  - Mussolini, Benito, 1928-1930 (Folder 14: 11)
  - Nicolas, Prince of Romania, 1923-1931 (Folder 14: 12)
  - Nicolson, Harold, 1924 (Folder 14: 13)
  - Osusky, Stefan, 1927 (Folder 14: 14)
  - Paul-Boncour, Joseph, 1924-1938 (Folder 14: 15)
  - Petrescu-Comnen, Nicolae, 1924-1931 (Folder 14: 16)
  - Poincaré, Raymond, 1922-1929 (Folder 14: 17)
  - Politis, N., 1926-1927 (Folder 14: 18)
  - Popescu, Stelian, 1937 (Folder 14: 19)
  - Radescu, Nicolae, 1924-1929 (Folder 14: 20)
  - Romania. Ministerul Afacerilor Strâine (Ministry of Foreign Affairs), 1922 (Folder 14: 21)
  - Romania. Ministerul Finantelor. Directiunea Datoriei Publice (Ministry of Finance. Directorate of Public Debts), 1923-1925 (Folder 14: 22)
  - Saint-Aulaire, n.d. (Folder 14: 23)
  - Skrzyński, 1925 (Folder 14: 24)
  - Société Internationale de Philologie, Sciences et Beaux-Arts (London), 1930 (Folder 14: 25)
  - Stamfordham, 1923 (Folder 14: 26)
  - Stirbey, Barbu, 1926-1927 (Folder 14: 27)
  - Stresemann Memorial Committee, 1931 (Folder 14: 28)
  - Sturdza, Mihail R., 1929-1930 (Folder 14: 29)
  - Tardieu, André, n.d. (Folder 14: 30)
  - Tatarescu, Gheorghe, 1930 (Folder 14: 31)
  - Thomas, Albert, n.d. (Folder 14: 32)
  - University of Bucarest. Law Department, 1930 (Folder 14: 33)
  - Venezuela. Legación (Switzerland), 1931 (Folder 14: 34)
  - Venizelos, Eleuthérios K., 1929 (Folder 14: 35)
  - Visoianu, Constantin, 1930-1931 (Folder 14: 36)
  - Miscellany (Folder 14: 37)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1925-1937., See also SUBJECT FILE/Petite Entente
  - "Memoriul asupra finanţelor României de la începtul razboiului şi pîna la pace," n.d. (Folder 14: 38)
    Holograph (in Romanian)
  - Speech before a group of American journalists in Geneva, Switzerland, n.d. (Folder 14: 39)
    Typescript (in English)
  - Speech, Columbia University, New York, 1925 January 6. (Folder 14: 40)
  - Speech, Société Internationale de Philologie, Sciences et Beaux Arts, London, 1929 May 20. (Folder 14: 41)
  - Address, Association des Étudiants Roumains en France, Paris, 1929 December 8. (Folder 14: 42)
    Typescript (in French)
  - "Benes," tribute to Edvard Benes, 1934. (Folder 14: 43)
    Holograph (in French). Published in Eduard Benes and the Petite Entente (Prague, 1934)
  - Speech for Louis Barthou at the dinner of the French Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 1934 June 20. (Folder 14: 44)
  - Speech before the Romanian Parliament at the reception for Louis Barthou in Bucarest, 1934 June 21. (Folder 14: 45)
  - Speech, Ankara, Turkey, 1934 October 30. (Folder 14: 46)
  - Speech before the Council of the League of Nations, Geneva, 1934 December 10. (Folder 14: 47)
  - Speech for departing Argentine Minister, 1936 June. (Folder 14: 48)
  - Speech for departing Papal Emissary, Valerio Valeri, 1936 June. (Folder 14: 49)
  - Speech honoring the heads of state of the Petite Entente, 1936 June 6. (Folder 14: 50)
  - Opening speech, Conférence Constitutive de la Presse de l'Entente Balkanique, Bucarest, 1936 June 11. (Folder 14: 51)
  - Speech for departing French Minister and response by Marquis d'Ormesson, 1936 June 15. (Folder 14: 52)
  - "La Commission Européenne du Danube," interview, Le Temps, 1936 July 30. (Folder 14: 53)
    Printed copy
  - "The Romanian Ministerial Crisis of August 1936," memoir written after August 1936. (Box-folder 15: 1-2)
    Typescript
  - "La situation générale européenne et l'avenir de la S.D.N," speech, Bordeaux, France, 1937 June 27. (Box-folder 16: 1)
    Typescript summary by Sud-Est Agence Télégraphique
- SUBJECT FILE, 1919-1947
  - Académie Diplomatique Internationale, 1926 (Folder 16: 2)
  - Barthou, Louis, speech, Bucarest, 1934 (in French) (Folder 16: 3)
  - Bratianu, Vintila, 1925 (Folder 16: 4)
  - Carol II, King of Romania
    - General (Folder 16: 5)
    - Letter to King George V, 1930 June 9 (Folder 16: 6)
  - Clemenceau, Georges. Clippings on his death, Le Temps, 1929 November 25 (Folder 16: 7)
  - Conference on Reparations (1930: Hague, Netherlands), 1929-1930 (Folder 16: 8)
  - Ferdinand, King of Romania
    - Distribution of property (Folder 16: 9)
    - Health. Telegrams, 1927 April (Folder 16: 10)
  - History. (Folder 16: 11)
    Speech by British historian Wickam Steady entitled "The Power of Historical Memory," n.d. Typescript
  - Hungary - Optants' dispute
    - 1924-1930 (Folder 16: 12-13)
    - 1928 (Folder 16: 14)
  - Ionescu, Barbu - Trial in London, 1930 February (Folder 16: 15)
  - Kellogg-Briand Pact (1928). (Folder 16: 16)
    Clipping, Le Temps, 1928 August 28
  - League of Nations
    - General (Folder 16: 17)
    - Information Section, 1924 (Folder 16: 18)
  - Lupescu, Magda (Folder 16: 19)
  - Minorities - Romania (Folder 16: 20)
  - Montreaux Conference on the Régime of the Straits (1936). (Folder 16: 21)
    Report by Romanian delegates, 1936 July 21 (in Romanian)
  - Petite Entente. (Folder 16: 22)
    Includes draft of press release in the hand of Edvard Benes, with corrections by Nicolae Titulescu
  - Romania
    - Foreign relations
      - Hungary, 1919-1930., See also Hungary (Folder 16: 23)
      - Soviet Union, 1936 July 21., See Soviet Union for 1931-1932 peace negotiations (Folder 16: 24)
        Pact of mutual assistance.
    - Politics and government. (Folder 16: 25)
      Telegram announcing the resignation of the government of Vintila Bratianu, 1928 November 3
  - Romania. Legatie (France) - Finances, 1921-1922 (Folder 16: 26-27)
  - Soviet Union - Foreign relations. (Box 17)
    Documents relating to peace negotiations with Romania, Poland, Finland, Estonia, and Latvia
    - 1929-1932 (Folder 17: 1)
    - 1931 November - 1932 January (Folder 17: 2)
    - 1931 December - 1932 January (Folder 17: 3)
    - 1932
      - January-April (Folder 17: 4)
      - April-October (Folder 17: 5)
      - August-October (Folder 17: 6)
  - Tatarescu, Gheorghe (Folder 17: 7)
  - Trials (Political crimes and offenses) - Romania. (Folder 17: 8)
    List of seven persons condemned to death in Bucarest and note relating to the disposition of Nicolae Titulescu's remains, 1947 (in French)
  - Ukraine. Mission (Paris), 1928 February 12 (Folder 17: 9)
  - University of Bucarest, 400th anniversary, 1931 May (Folder 17: 10)
  - Miscellany. (Folder 17: 11)
    Pamphlet by I. Corbu entitled The Origin of Continents, Red Spot of Jupiter, the Solar System, and the Formation of America, 1931 (in French)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, n.d.
  - One print of a painting by Brenner depicting the inn in Talloires, France, where Nicolae Titulescu met secretly with Maksim Litvinov on May 28, 1937 (Folder 17: 12)
  - One print of a portrait depicting Nicolae Titulescu, n.d. (Photo-file envelope A)
- MICROFILM, n.d. (Microfilm-cabinet Microfilm cabinet)